(♪♪♪)
OFFICER 1:
Blacklance, step up.
(♪♪♪)
OFFICER 2:
All right, Richie,
you're good to go.
(♪♪♪)
LEON:
Hey, over here.
I think they're over here.
LEON:
Go, go, go.
Up on the cliff.
(♪♪♪)
LEON:
Al, why'd you stop?
Oh, shit.
(♪♪♪)
TEDDY:
Yeah, I saw then
that it was Bradley.
Albert's brother.
I know the family,
so I'll make the notification.
Okay.
(POLICE RADIO CHATTER)
COMMENTATOR (ON RADIO):
(INDISTINCT SPEECH)
Hold the ball.
Look at your stride
once in a while,
just to offset the timing
and tempo of the baseline.
Hey, Dad.
Hey.
(CHUCKLES)
Stop.
Practice tomorrow?
Yeah, 6:30.
TEDDY:
Need a ride?
Nah, it's all good.
Coach is gonna swing by
and give me a lift there.
TEDDY:
Albert found him in the woods
behind the clubhouse.
DYANI:
I just can't believe it.
His mother and now his brother?
(SIGHS)
You okay?
Yeah, it's just...
I know.
I'm here.
(KISSES)
DYANI (VO):
You're a good man, Teddy.
TEDDY (VO):
I just look at Albert
and I see our boy.
I see all those kids.
(♪♪♪)
(EXHALES SMOKE)
What the...
I got ya. Hurry!
(♪♪♪)
There he is.
(INDISCERNIBLE SPEECH)
And boom. You wanna make
that elbow
about 90 degrees with your eye.
(♪♪♪)
STERLING:
You really clean?
RICHIE:
Cigarettes. That's it.
Hardest to kick.
STERLING:
State Pen did you good.
Not the pen.
Place makes you wanna be
swinging from the ceiling.
It was the brothers
I was with.
OG natives.
Real men.
STERLING:
That's what I needed, bro.
Mentors and shit.
Ain't nothing
but kids out here, bro.
Guys like us, we're like,
OGs in these streets now.
Isn't that crazy?
(MOANING)
(PUFFS SMOKES)
Yeah, I can't quit.
Not before I do work.
(MOANING)
Yo, I'm home.
(EXHALES)
What's up, Winchell?
Richie.
When'd you get out?
Yesterday.
Thought we'd throw
a welcome home party.
(♪♪♪)
Still in your old line
of work, huh?
Gotta pay rent somehow.
Heard you're repping D.E.P.
Finally picked a side.
The wrong side.
You know how it is, man.
Can't last as an independent
in this game.
(♪♪♪)
How does
a two-bit tweaker dealer
get the blessing of Luke
Spencer to join the Posse?
Just comes down to money.
RICHIE:
Yeah. It always does.
How much did Luke pay you
to sell me tainted dope?
WINCHELL:
Richie.
No, don't. Not to him.
RICHIE:
You know,
I don't blame anyone
for wanting me dead.
That's just the price of
being a player in the game.
But my sister?
Look, I was threatened
if I didn't--
How'd I know your sister
was gonna be the one
to take your dope and go--
(GROANS)
(CHOKES)
What are you doing?
No, no! No! No! No!
(GRUNTING)
(SCREAMS)
RICHIE:
You know what's crazy?
You and I used to kick it
and play video games
all the time as kids.
(GROANS)
Sleepovers and shit.
(WINCHELL GROANS)
Please, Richie.
(WINCHELL CHOKES)
Let's get the fuck outta here.
-Shit.
-Oh, shit.
-Chill, man. I got this.
Hey, officer.
They went that way.
Hey, take a step back
from the vehicle.
Chill, man.
We're the ones that called you.
Step back from the vehicle.
Show me your hands.
Hands out of your po--
(SCREAMING)
(♪♪♪)
(SIGHS, GRUNTS)
(INDISCERNIBLE CHATTER)
NEWSREADER (ON RADIO):
Three people are dead,
including
a rookie police officer,
at a grisly scene
in the city's north side.
At a press conference
earlier this morning,
Chief Jerry Garland confirmed
that the department
is on the hunt
for two unknown suspects,
who are believed
to be connected
to native street gangs
from the troubled
Thunderstone Reservation.
Tribal Police
and Reliance County
Sheriff's Department
have both pledged
their full cooperation,
despite last month's
very public dispute
over criminal jurisdiction
of tribal land.
Police have stressed
that the two suspects
are believed to be
armed and dangerous.
♪ Three, two, one ♪
♪ When we were young ♪
♪ There were so many
new things ♪
♪ For us to find ♪
♪ And time was never
on our mind ♪
So, no barrier from the perps?
Nah, I took that shit out.
Put the regular seats back in.
Where you from?
Tulsa, Oklahoma.
Yeah, I know that.
I mean your people.
I'm American.
Oh.
What is it, Scala?
What is that, Italian?
You, uh, celebrate Columbus Day
and all that?
I'm Greek.
Well, we're all just
squatters here, Toto.
Wait, you're not...
Nope.
Grew up over the line.
They used to bus some kids
into my school from the res,
and I was too poor
and too brown
for the white kids,
so they lumped me in
with the natives.
And then I married me one.
(CHUCKLES)
Ah.
It was the '80s.
Shit was crazy.
(LAUGHS)
Got any Indians out there
in Tulsa?
Uh, the indigenous people
there are--
Indians.
I don't think we're supposed
to say--
Oh, don't do that, rookie.
You might hurt yourself.
I've got four years on.
In a bigger department
than this, so--
Bigger ain't shit.
This is tribal land.
And lose that PC bullshit
they drilled into your brain
in the big city.
That shit don't jive out here,
all right?
Indigenous.
Is that what they are now?
According to who? You?
Hmm?
Your white college professor?
Some pretendian who's never
even been to the res?
Listen, you take
that colonizer guilt bullshit
and you bury it somewhere
deep because I'll tell you,
when you're in a foot chase
down here,
you're gonna be yelling out
her description like,
(MIMICS PANTING)
"Indian male,
running northbound fast!
He's, uh, approximately 5'10",
130 pounds, red skin, feather,
armed with a tomahawk!"
(LAUGHS)
Oh, shit. Relax, Toto.
Oh, these are tough people
out here.
No one's gonna get offended
by some here today,
gone tomorrow
Greek rookie res cop.
DISPATCHER (ON RADIO):
Bravo 5-5, Bravo 5-5.
You waiting
for smoke signals?
Oh.
Go for Bravo 5-5.
DISPATCHER (ON RADIO):
Bravo 5-5, neighbors advising
of trespassers
inside a vacant house.
It's the, uh,
doublewide Marty Powers
got stabbed in
back in October.
-Can we get an address?
-I know where it's at.
♪ Until our time slips away ♪
♪ Slips away ♪
TEDDY:
Relax.
I'll go first and I don't need
a bullet in my back.
A lot of these vacant homes
don't even have
addresses anymore.
So what do I do
if I need backup
and I don't know
where Marty Power got stabbed?
I don't know.
Fifth house on the left,
look for my car,
the lights are on.
You'll figure it out.
Feds built some homes
closer to town.
That's where old Marty Powers
is now.
They promised
clean running water.
They're taking
their time though.
Meanwhile, every passing hobo
and meth head
finds these empty places
to hang loose for a while.
Who's in there?
Don't surprise me,
motherfucker,
or you'll get shot!
Go after him.
SAMMY:
Go, hurry, hurry, come on.
Go, go, go, go, go!
TEDDY:
Hold it!
Let me see those hands.
Turn around.
Let me see you.
(LAUGHS)
Look at these
two criminal masterminds.
Jordy P is his nickname.
VM for Vice Mob.
Sometimes they brand out here
along with the gang ink.
22 for V, 13 for M.
(LAUGHS)
Jordy, you are literally
a walking mugshot.
Watch him.
See a lot of D.E.P. out here.
Dead End Posse.
Hmm. Clever.
Mace. Nice catch.
Next customer.
Going into your pockets,
anything gonna stick me?
I don't think so.
Mm-hmm.
This doesn't qualify?
This is why I love my job.
You know what I just did?
Hey, keep your hands out
of your pockets, please.
I just prevented the robbing
of a gas station,
the stabbing
of some I.B.N. loser,
or potentially one of these
two numpties getting shot
by the police.
I am a goddamn hero.
SANDRA:
All right, let me get some IDs.
No, no, no.
We're not doing that.
You go immediately home.
If I find either one of you
back out here
or anywhere else
other than home today,
I promise you,
you will be remanded.
I will make sure that happens
one way or another.
Beat it.
Sorry, weren't we supposed
to run them for, like,
wants and warrants, conditions?
I mean, they're gang members.
Isn't that, like--
Yeah, sure.
Sammy could go in
on a weapons violation.
But tomorrow, his mom is headed
to the city for work
and Sammy watches
her five-year-old twins
during the day.
Jordy P. is wanted
in the city for assault.
I mean, they might come
down here and get him.
Or hell, shit, man,
we might just take him up
there ourselves.
But I'd rather save that
for a rainy day.
A rainy day?
(LAUGHS)
What was your last
department like?
It was blue collar.
It was a tough beat to work.
Yeah, well,
out here it's no collar.
No backup, no resources,
no witnesses.
I mean, hell, sometimes
it's even hard to find a victim.
Res policing is all
about temporary problem solving,
favors and leverage.
You get everyone
in this town through
to the end of the shift
and then you hand the reins
over to the next schmuck.
All right, let's find a dumpster
and process those exhibits.
Teddy.
Uh-huh.
-So you're the new girl?
-Hmm. Sandra.
Darius.
I'm with Reliance County.
Dispatch informed us
about the call.
You guys good?
SANDRA:
Yeah, we're good.
Mm-hmm.
Well, it is a beautiful, crisp,
cool day.
Nothing like some shit rats
to keep us warm and busy, huh?
All right,
call if you need anything.
SANDRA:
Yeah, no, it's--
it's just not what I expected.
My partner is definitely
a character.
(SANDRA CHUCKLES)
No, Mom, don't.
Because I just got here.
You know,
I haven't even settled in yet.
I still need
to get my bearings.
How's Dad doing?
Can I talk to him?
Yeah, no, it's fine.
I-- I know he's busy.
Maybe tomorrow.
Hey, listen, I'm gonna go, uh,
get some sleep.
I'm exhausted.
CEREMONY LEADER:
(SINGS IN NATIVE LANGUAGE)
(♪♪♪)
DUNCAN:
It seems we never stop
mourning, doesn't it?
Chelsea, you've experienced
so much loss over the years,
so much heartache.
It's too much for one person
to bear.
You've raised and guided
our kids in this town.
Even when my own boys
were running amok,
causing me havoc,
they'd come to you
for advice about their troubles.
You were the most
resilient person they knew.
We've always had
to be resilient.
So please believe me
when I say when you hurt,
we all hurt.
When you weep, we all weep.
Chelsea.
CHELSEA:
Luke.
What are you doing here, Luke?
Can't you see
she's going through enough?
You show your face here
of all places--
Don't trip.
I'm not here to cause trouble.
Had no beef with Bradley.
Just paying my respects.
You need to leave, Luke.
ANGEL:
Bye.
Rumor is Richie got parole.
Heard stories he's running wild
in the big city.
Heard he might be headed
this way.
-Richie isn't here--
-Richie isn't here.
Richie is not welcome
anywhere near any of us.
I buried a lot of my family,
but he is the only one
who is dead to me.
Then we're good.
Sorry for your loss.
Bradley was a good kid.
(♪♪♪)
CHELSEA:
Who's that?
(♪♪♪)
Hey, Mom.
What do you want?
That's all you had to say?
After all these years?
Bradley...
He's been on my mind a lot.
Wish I could see him
one more time.
I know it's gotta be
killing Albert.
How is he?
You leave him alone.
You've done enough.
You really still blame me?
For every problem
this family has?
(SCOFFS)
RICHIE:
Like Leanne didn't show me
how to get high?
Like Leroy didn't show me
how to boost cars?
Just leave.
(TAKES A DRAG AND PUFFS SMOKE)
All these dead
and broken kids, Mom.
What does that say about you?
(♪♪♪)
SANDRA:
A lot of calls come
in through here?
It's the heart
of gang territory.
But only two crews
have any real teeth.
Dead End Posse
and Indian Blood Nation.
Bull.
Teddy.
He's I.B.N.
(♪♪♪)
TRUNK GANGSTER:
What?
You want me to pop this thing
and get you some air?
TRUNK GANGSTER:
Who the fuck is this?
The police. You want out
of this thing or what?
TRUNK GANGSTER:
Ah, shit, man, why are you
harassing me for, dude?
Harassing you?
You're locked in a trunk.
TRUNK GANGSTER:
Is that a crime, officer?
What, you got a warrant?
No one's asking
for your help.
Leave me the fuck alone
to do my time.
All right. Conserve your air.
TRUNK GANGSTER:
Conserve my dick, pig!
Fucking harassment.
You're just gonna leave
him there?
Yeah, he must've done
something to piss Bull off.
We have our laws
and punishments,
streets have theirs.
Where's my boy?
Coach has been keeping 'em late
at practice all week,
getting ready
for the big tournament.
-Oh, yeah? What sport?
-Basketball.
Oh.
He's pretty good too.
He swears he's got
that Mamba mentality.
If he learns to control
that temper of his.
Oh, and how long did it take
you to control yours?
(TEDDY CHUCKLES)
Teddy was a hothead
in his heydays.
I'm still in my heydays.
-He isn't.
-Ouch.
(SANDRA GIGGLES)
Sandra,
you should've seen him.
If a boy did
a double take of me
when I walked by,
Teddy would lose
his ever-lovin' mind.
I used to call him Teddy Bear.
I was 15.
But my parents
called him Grizzly Bear.
They liked him.
Liked that I had
a young warrior protecting me.
They were pretty shocked
to find out
he was half Filipino.
(CHUCKLES)
So you guys got one boy?
Mm, one boy, four girls.
Oh, wow!
(DYANI CHUCKLES)
Yeah, the girls
are all grown up,
scattered all over the place.
Jeffrey was our happy accident.
TEDDY:
All right.
Don't be thinking every shift
we're gonna have time
to sit down and eat,
let alone at home.
You just lucked out.
Not much going on today?
No, it's been pretty quiet.
(EXHALES)
Think I may have
just jinxed us.
DYANI:
Can I ask you a question?
Sure.
Well, I look at you
and I don't see cop.
I mean, I know you were one,
are one, but now Tribal?
How does that happen?
Wasn't my first choice.
TEDDY:
No shit.
Well, I come
from a family of cops.
You know, they were the ones
with like the cop-themed cakes
at the birthday parties,
lots of testosterone
flying around.
You know, my dad had just
been promoted to deputy chief
when I put in
for the department.
He didn't like the idea of me
rolling around
the gutter with the bad guys,
so I told him
it's either his department
where he can keep an eye on me,
or somewhere else.
All right. But why here?
Why Tribal?
I guess his, uh,
shadow was harder
to come out from under
than I thought it would be.
And I also just kinda wanted
to be somewhere far
and, uh, different.
I mean, there's more to it
than that,
but that's the gist of it.
DYANI:
Well, I think your father
should be proud.
Right, Ted?
He likes you. I can tell.
Trust me.
Otherwise, you would be sitting
in the car while he ate.
I'm serious.
I have seen him do it before.
What was...
What was that guy's name,
the deputy?
Dumphrey.
DYANI:
So Ted here has the boy
sit in the cop car
while he ate
and napped on the couch.
(CHUCKLING)
DISPATCHER (ON RADIO):
Incoming Priority One.
All units attend.
Sorry, sorry.
I'll pack these up.
TEDDY:
You're looking for Northeast
14th. Tell me where to turn.
-Which road are we on right now?
-TEDDY: 4th parallel south.
DISPATCHER (ON RADIO):
Patching you over to Sheriff's
Department to get you back up.
I swear to God,
if they beat us to our call,
you are walking back
to the station.
How many have we passed so far?
How many roads?
Uh, three.
Oh, shit! Turn!
DISPATCHER (ON RADIO):
Caller has identified suspect
as Elan Graves.
Says he had
to leave the scene
since the suspect's firing off
shots at random.
Female is out front,
in need of medical assistance.
TEDDY:
Shit.
This is gonna be bad.
Elan is highly unstable.
Jesus.
He beat her half to death.
Faint.
You administer CPR.
I'm gonna go clear the house.
Make sure you know
what you're looking at.
They got two boys.
SANDRA:
Bravo 5-5, Code 9, 901 Nora.
Scene not secure.
Have fire stage south
of our cruiser lights.
Making entry, 10-33.
(♪♪♪)
Tribal Police!
Elan, if you're in here,
make yourself known!
(♪♪♪)
Let me see your hands, Elan!
Don't move, motherfucker!
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Hey, guys.
Everyone all right over here?
Anybody hurt?
ELAN'S BOY:
No.
Okay, good.
I'm gonna be right back.
If you guys could just hang
in here for me.
All right.
Take care of your
little brother, okay?
(SIGHS)
Code 4?
Bathroom, deceased.
You okay?
Oh, shit. Richie.
RICHIE:
What's up, nephew?
Richie, you're back.
Come-- come to the front.
I'll let you in.
Shit, man. You trying to get us
both killed?
Nah, your grandma wouldn't
like that.
Come through
the window then.
Listen, me and some boys
are gonna pay respects
to your brother.
I want you to come
and meet them.
-Right now?
-Yeah.
C'mon. I'll have you back
before anyone notices.
Hey, grab a jacket, it's cold.
I should tell Grandma, though.
She won't care if I tell her
I'm going to--
She doesn't have to know.
You're the man
of this house now anyways.
There's no asking permission,
all right?
Damn, bro. You got big.
(LAUGHS)
Shut up, fool.
All right.
All right, Al, let's go.
GANG MEMBER 1:
Man, I shut the fuck up, man.
All I do is bitch.
(INDISCERNIBLE SPEECH)
What's up, dawg?
-Bruv.
-Good to see you, man.
What's up, brother?
Good to see you out, brother.
You didn't last long
in the city.
Yeah.
Had to pop off
on an old friend.
That's the word on the street.
We'll break y'all some cash
and get you situated.
Appreciate it.
Y'all know my nephew, Albert.
Brad's brother.
What's up, young blood?
I knew your brother.
He was a strong native.
I wish he would've rode with us.
Could've helped him
with some of his troubles.
You got real Indian blood
in you, warrior blood.
I wanna make sure
he's taken care of.
I want him to have family.
You might've lost a brother,
but with us, you gain a 100.
Your brother could use that.
We all do growing up
in this bullshit.
(♪♪♪)
Yeah.
Yeah?
Cold-blooded motherfucker.
Join the Nation? Why not, huh?
This is brotherhood right here.
Come here, cuz.
Welcome to the family.
Family now, boy.
It's a good thing.
(♪♪♪)
(POLICE RADIO CHATTER)
Why don't you go home
and get some rest?
I'll finish this up.
TEDDY:
You okay?
Yeah.
It's gonna happen a lot.
(MUNCHES)
People trying to find a way
to forget the past.
The drink.
Needle.
That gonna be a problem?
Same everywhere it seems.
Yeah, so I've heard.
Then, uh, no, sir,
it's not gonna be a problem.
TEDDY:
Did you do it for him
or for your father?
What?
Your boyfriend.
(POLICE RADIO CHATTER)
When you found him that day
and cleaned him up,
was it for his dignity
or for Daddy's career?
Honestly, sir, you don't know
anything about that.
TEDDY:
No?
Tell me, what am I missing?
There's more to someone
than what they put on a report.
So, tell me.
(EXHALES)
Cops drink. That's normal.
Working undercover narcotics
changed him.
(POLICE RADIO CHATTER)
He started stealing dope
from the evidence lockers.
I came home
from a night shift once,
found him face down
in the bathroom,
still with that fucking thing
in his arm,
just like that asshole
from today.
And?
I cleaned him up.
I searched the house,
I found the stash.
I destroyed it.
I didn't want him
to be remembered for that.
My dad made some calls,
got me a quiet resignation,
but he took a big hit,
and so did our relationship.
Look, I love being a cop.
I don't know
what my dad told you
or any of the other departments
I applied to,
but I appreciate
the opportunity.
I hired you
because I need a partner
who can look past the bullshit
and understand why people are
the way they are.
That's what
this community needs.
That's what you needed.
And, so did I.
Different time,
same problems, Toto.
Think you can do that?
Good.
Crazy night, huh?
- Oh, hey.
- I'm Katie, by the way.
We didn't officially meet.
Sandra.
We're having a drink out
in town, little dive bar.
Team debrief. You should come.
I, uh, actually got
some unpacking to do
at my place still, so...
I don't know how you did it
at your last department,
sweetheart, but out here,
drinking might as well be
in our policy and procedures.
Especially being new.
Come on. Have a drink or two.
DARIUS:
It rips the fucking shirt,
clean off his back,
splits the seam
on the cheap piece of shit.
So now he's free again.
He's off,
he's running down
the middle of the street,
this shirtless, shoeless,
fucking gap-toothed,
drunk Indian,
making a fool out of me.
I'm just getting madder,
all right?
I'm getting madder and madder.
I pull my fucking taser out,
right?
I give him
fair warning, too, like,
"Stop! You're gonna get tased."
Boom.
Dude gets hit
by a fucking truck.
(LAUGHING)
Right there, sends him in
the air, limp like a rag doll.
He lands
and he slides to my feet.
PHIL:
Oh, shit.
To my fucking feet.
Hand delivered.
PHIL:
Damn. Wow.
I cuff the Indian,
told the farmer to beat it.
How's Teddy treating you?
Good.
PHIL:
What nickname did he give you?
Toto.
Toto?
Like the dog?
Like-- like Dorothy?
PHIL:
It's not that bad actually.
Remember what he called Darius?
DARIUS:
Oh, my God, yeah.
He called him Dumphrey.
SANDRA:
I don't get it.
(RONNIE AND BRETT LAUGH)
PHIL:
Darius Humphrey.
Do I--
do I even wanna know or...
Dumphrey.
BRETT:
Dude shit his pants
stirred in a res.
So, wait, that was you?
DARIUS:
No.
I'm sorry.
Laziest fuck in a department
of lazy fucks.
KATIE:
Come on, relax.
Mm, I mean, I--
I started in Tribal Police.
Gave up on that shit real quick.
-Switched to a real department.
-Don't listen to him.
Teddy's good people.
He knows everybody front
and back.
People respect him,
in town and on the res,
despite the jurisdictional
nonsense.
Yeah, they used to.
And that's the problem,
he's trying to win
everybody back over.
The guy won't arrest
an Indian to save
his fucking life.
Dude's not even native.
KATIE:
Shut up. He's got more pinches
than all of you combined.
Maybe from back in the day.
Yeah, Katie, you know damn good
and well he is not
the skull crusher
that he allegedly once was.
When was the last time
he went out
for a beer with us, huh?
Or just done anything
with the boys?
KATIE:
I don't give a shit.
He'll come running
if you need help.
Who cares about the rest?
Yeah, maybe.
Or maybe one day
he just decides,
"Hey, I'm gonna back one of my
old Listerine-drinking buddies."
You know?
Yeah, he is one dicey move away
from being run outta town
for good.
So, what actually happened
with Teddy?
'Cause I heard a bunch
of crazy different stories.
Mm, no, we're not gonna
go there, babe.
Did you apply to our department?
DARIUS:
Hmm, what, they didn't take you?
I don't know. Must be cursed.
Shit, girl. What skeletons
you got in your closet?
Ooh.
DARIUS:
Just a joke.
I don't know, Katie,
maybe you're right.
Maybe she's not a dud.
Oh!
(GROANS, GASPS)
(GRUNTS)
(LAUGHS)
SANDRA:
So whose house is this?
TEDDY (VO):
This woman holds this community
together single-handedly.
She is everyone's family
on this reservation,
you hear me?
She buried her
grandson yesterday,
and then she took in those boys
from the domestic last night.
ELAN'S BOY 2:
Stop that.
TEDDY:
Oh, yeah?
ELAN'S BOY 2:
Stop eating my chips.
(INDISTINCT SPEECH)
All right, don't hurt anyone.
CHELSEA:
This is my oldest son, Leroy.
They sent him to fight in Iraq.
Gave his life,
killed in action.
This is Leanne, my daughter,
Albert and Bradley.
She died from a heroin
overdose five years ago.
SANDRA:
I'm so sorry.
CHELSEA:
But she gave me the most
beautiful grandchildren.
(♪♪♪)
Hey, Albert.
Albert.
(SIGHS)
Teddy, it scares me what
that boy is going through,
what it's gonna mean for him
and his life.
We'll look out for him.
You have to promise me.
Promise me, you have to.
I promise.
Teddy, he doesn't blame you
for what happened.
None of us do.
I know. I know.
There's something else.
What? What is it?
It's Richie. He's here.
Come in.
Hmm.
Those remind me
of the training academy.
What are they for?
Uh, it's part
of my cadet uniform.
Cadet? What's that?
Uh, it was a program for kids.
Really? Y-- you mind if I...
Uh, yeah.
Teddy used to run it
with someone else,
and he was Sergeant Major.
Teddy as Sergeant Major?
Explains a whole lot to me.
Oh wow, yeah, this is perfect.
Yeah, you'd pass
training inspection for sure.
- Oh yeah?
- Yeah, trust me,
I failed plenty of them,
so I'm well versed.
DISPATCHER (ON RADIO):
Bravo 5-5, respond
to KSRC community center
for a 242F, multiple CPs.
ALBERT:
So, you live around here?
TEDDY (ON RADIO):
Bravo 5-5, 10-4.
Uh, no. I'm just in town.
So you're working with Teddy?
SANDRA:
Yes.
TEDDY:
Gotta go, partner.
We got a call.
Nice to meet you, Albert.
You too.
Seems like a good kid.
He's got that whole, uh,
cadet thing going.
Doesn't exist anymore.
What? Why not?
Light 'em up.
(♪♪♪)
This used to be
where the community met.
For everything.
Pow wows, events, ceremonies.
Past 15 years,
every kid growing up
in Thunderstone spent
all their free time here.
They used to call it
"The Clubhouse".
(JAKE HOWLS
AND LAUGHS IN DISTANCE)
(EXHALES)
He might fight.
If he does, it's gonna be
a bad night.
You know who that is?
Jake! Jake, it's Teddy.
JAKE:
Teddy, where are you?
Out front, Jake.
JAKE:
Fuck you!
He should be okay.
He didn't sound that bad.
Just be cautious.
JAKE:
Fuck it, bro.
Sergeant Major!
TEDDY:
All right. Be careful now.
What are you doing here?
We having a reunion?
TEDDY:
Someone called about you.
I guess you're being too loud.
You're gonna arrest me?
You wanna throw me in jail?
-I ain't got any warrants.
-I know.
JAKE:
Check the computer.
Look for yourself.
I know. You're a standup guy.
Bring another outsider
to town, Teddy?
Another fucking wolf
to feed us to?
TEDDY:
Now, now, Jake.
There's no need for that.
How about you put down
that bottle
and we can drive you home?
Fuck that.
I ain't done drinking.
I'm telling you,
you are, Jake.
Look at you
trying to playing cop now.
I thought you were supposed
to be protecting us.
Good job there.
(GRUNTS)
(SPITS)
Come on. Let's fucking go.
SANDRA:
So what's the deal
with all the shit
he was saying back there?
I started my career
as a state trooper.
My first posting for the force
was up north.
Small detachment.
24-hour on call.
Place like that depend on more
than just the cops, you know?
Kinda like it is here.
You learn to trust
certain people,
volunteer firefighters,
paramedics.
(♪♪♪)
Met a man up there
named Leslie West.
Everyone called him Coach.
He was originally a teacher
from the East Coast, uh, Maine.
Did a lot of good up there.
Seemed like he really
gave a shit.
First he did a year stint,
and then he came back
for three more,
and we were lucky to have him.
You know, he ran sports teams,
he ran clubs,
took part in everything.
We became friends
pretty quick.
A couple of outsiders, around
the same age, trying to help.
-Oh, he's fooled you.
-Hoo-hoo-hoo!
When I found out there was
an opportunity for me
to come home, well, you know,
I took it
and I-- I sold him
on coming with me.
You know,
he was the kind of guy
who did that sort of thing,
just drop everything
for a challenge.
But before we got down here,
we had already
started organizing
that Cadet program.
Like what Albert had?
TEDDY:
Yeah.
Put a real dent in some
of the gang recruitment,
the drugs, the booze.
We had every young man
in the community taking part.
I mean, I even-- I even got
some ex-gang members I knew
to come and mentor.
Created a real sense of pride.
(JAKE MUMBLING)
We found out a couple years
back that Coach
was sexually assaulting several
of the boys in the program.
13 came forward.
Who knows how many haven't
out of shame or embarrassment?
Once he got arrested,
a lot of the kids up north
started speaking up too.
They're looking into his
classes back East still,
trying to see how far back
he started.
So the center closed,
the Cadets disbanded,
kids went back
to the street gangs
and the vultures picked up
right where we left off.
(♪♪♪)
So what happened to Leslie?
Was he convicted?
He got bail.
And then he went straight
to his office
and blew his brains out
with a hunting rifle
he had stashed there, I guess,
for exactly that purpose.
He-- he wasn't around
for Albert, right?
He was.
His brother, too.
Bradley was a victim.
He came forward.
Albert never said if he was,
but he was right on the cusp
of Leslie's preferred age.
JAKE:
The fuck you say his name for?
I'm just talking, Jake.
She needs to mind
her own business.
You ain't even from around here.
Okay.
JAKE:
Mind your own fucking business!
Jake.
JAKE:
Keep quiet.
Right, Teddy?
Isn't that what Coach
used to say?
Keep fucking quiet!
TEDDY:
Yeah.
Looks like it's time
for bed, Jake.
JAKE:
Get me the fuck out of here.
I got him.
Get your hands off.
How could you have known?
I should've known.
They're blaming you for trying
to make things better.
Everybody here hates you
because of that uniform.
It doesn't matter
if it's fair or not.
They hate you
because someone close to them
wears it and let the fox
in the henhouse.
This uniform stripped away
their language, their history,
their families.
And then someone they trust
wears it and pretends like
it's all different now.
Coach undid it all.
A generation of fucked up boys
turning into fucked up men.
You remember that.
You remember why they hate you
and why they are allowed to.
And then you go on every call
to help them,
not to prove them wrong.
NATHAN:
My mom found that bottle of
Jack that was under my bed.
-STEVEN: Yeah.
-It was not a good scene, man.
It was just yelling,
and screaming, and everything.
My dad was just sitting there
all quiet and stuff.
I don't know
what he really thought
about the whole situation.
Oh, fuck, dude, just--
just keep on walking.
Yeah.
Fuck, dude.
I.B.N. GANG MEMBER:
Hey, yo, yo, what's up?
Hey, where the party at?
NATHAN:
Hey, no, man, no party tonight.
We're just heading home.
I.B.N. GANG MEMBER:
Hey, do I know you?
Where you from?
Yeah, I know you.
Luke's brother, right?
STEVEN:
Fuck.
Richie, we don't want
any trouble, man.
Yeah, tell it to your
bitch ass brother then.
Remember what I said.
STEVEN:
Look, whatever beef you
and Luke got,
I ain't with that shit.
-Where you going?
-Wait, Richie.
Fuck, where you going?
(GROANS)
Here he is, nephew.
Time to check in.
Time to get that payback.
Please, no. Please!
Quick and easy. Just poke him.
Come on! Stick him!
For your mom!
His family laced that shit
on purpose to get at us!
STEVEN:
Wait, please. Please!
Shut the fuck up.
I'll break your neck.
Come on. Do it.
Listen. Stop!
Whatever my brother did,
I'm sorry.
They fucking killed her.
Stop. Stop.
(GRUNTS)
(GROANS, SCREAMS)
One more! One more.
(STEVEN CRYING)
(GROANS)
Hey.
You all right? You good?
(GROANS)
I.B.N. GANG MEMBER:
Fuck D.E.P!
(GROANING)
(POLICE RADIO CHATTER)
DARIUS:
Right, so who's out
shanking kids
who aren't even banging?
PARAMEDIC: Hey, we gotta go.
TEDDY:
Yeah.
SANDRA:
He's not saying much.
Says his memory's foggy.
Oh.
Your friend's likely gonna die
on his way to the hospital,
but snitches
get stitches, right?
NATHAN:
Teddy.
You call yourself a man?
It was Chelsea's kid.
Richie?
He was there,
but he didn't hold the knife.
Albert?
NATHAN:
Yeah.
You sure it wasn't Richie?
You really think
I'd mistake that animal
for someone else?
Richie held him in place
while the other kid
fucking stabbed him.
Initiation?
NATHAN:
What do you think?
SANDRA:
All right, hang back here
for a sec.
NATHAN:
Looks like
he's finally following in
his brother's footsteps.
Looks like a gang initiation.
For who?
The Nation.
Who's the new addition?
I don't know,
but it sounds like
Richie's back in town though.
Richie Blacklance?
When did he get out?
Over a week ago now.
Last I heard,
he was the Nation's enforcer
in the city.
DARIUS:
Shit, he's probably involved
with killing that cop up there.
He's gonna link up
with his crew.
We should get eyes on Bull,
on, uh, on T-Boy.
Yeah, he may have come back
for Brad's funeral
or maybe for Luke.
There's bad blood there.
So again,
who were they initiating?
(♪♪♪)
Luke, stop!
Don't make me overreact.
How you doing, Luke?
-I'm all right, officer.
-Yeah?
So what are you doing on this
side of town at this hour?
-Just visiting some friends.
-Quit your bullshit.
What happens if I turn you
upside down right now, huh?
You wanna bet
a burner falls out?
Stop fucking around.
I just saw your brother
before he got lifted
to the city.
You should be driving there,
not here.
He's a fucking civilian.
He's not involved in this shit.
They crossed the line.
You know who's
in that house right now?
Chelsea and Elan Graves'
two little boys.
Now, who are you looking
to clap up to get even?
I'm not looking for them.
Yeah?
Who do you expect to be
in that house, tough guy?
-The other one.
-Richie?
She'd kill Richie
before he got any closer
to that house than you and I
are right now.
(SCOFFS)
What? What's so goddamn funny?
Richie will get his.
He wants to blame me
for his sister OD'ing?
Fine, I'm ready.
I know the game.
It's his nephew
that got involved
when he shouldn't have.
Put in dirt,
you ain't innocent anymore.
This won't stop what's coming.
If I see you anywhere
near here again,
I am putting you down,
no warning,
and I'll plant
this fucking thing
on your corpse,
I swear to God.
It's like that?
TEDDY:
It's like that.
Maybe you'll catch on someday
that I am trying
to stop this bullshit going
in endless circles.
I'll be sure to let the boys
know you're picking sides.
I don't give a shit
what you tell
your dopey meth-head dwarfs.
If anyone fucks with Chelsea
or Albert, I'll kill all of you.
Am I free to go, officer?
You go and get out of here.
LUKE:
Be sure to tell Chelsea,
don't bother putting
her black wardrobe up.
What the fuck was that?
Why isn't he in handcuffs?
The only way to control his
crew and this town
is through him.
If we put him in the bin,
we lose
all line of communication,
and that house gets shot up
or-- or burned down
with those boys in it.
Line of communication?
What the fuck?
Everyone knows Albert
did the stabbing.
We can't go around
defending every family
of shithead kids
getting mixed up in gangs.
You think the same kid
polishing his boots
stabbed that boy?
It doesn't matter!
We just took a gun
off of a gang member
who was on his way
to assassinate a rival
and we let him go.
All right, this isn't about
good pinches, or--
or good charges, or--
or career progression.
This is about stopping
this shit,
even if it's just for a night.
Charges do that.
Prison does that.
What prison would do to Albert
would just mean more killing
in 5 or 10 years.
It stops nothing.
Did you find him?
Who?
Albert.
I called the station about him.
He-- he-- he said he was going
out with his friend Leon
and then, and-- and then he--
he hasn't come home yet.
So I-- I called Leon's parents
and-- and he--
He never went there.
What, Teddy?
Some boys got jumped tonight.
Luke's brother Steven
got stabbed.
They say they saw Richie.
(SIGHS)
TEDDY:
And they said
Albert was there too.
Now, you need to call me
if he comes home, all right,
'cause we're gonna be out
there looking for him.
All right, Chelsea.
Chelsea, stop. Stop.
Stop it, Chelsea.
No!
Okay?
All right, all right,
listen to me.
Look at me, look at me.
You need to stay here.
You have those boys
you have to look after.
And I need someone here
in case he comes back.
You call me directly. Okay?
(CRYING)
He wouldn't hurt anyone.
He would only hurt himself.
I know. I know.
CHELSEA:
You-- you bring him home to me!
You don't bring him
to the station.
You bring him home!
(CRYING)
This is cheating.
(INDISTINCT SPEECH)
(CHUCKLES)
BULL:
Yo! Turn that shit down.
If you wanna party,
you can find someplace else
to crash.
Or spend the night
in the trunk.
My bad. My bad, little man.
You got lucky.
I'm gonna head out for a smoke.
You mean a cigarette, right?
Don't bring that other shit
-around my house.
-Yeah, yeah.
(SCREAMS)
Police! (INDISTINCT SPEECH)
PHIL:
Police! Police!
Get inside now. Go, go, go!
Go, go!
(INDISTINCT SPEECH) Move!
Get inside! Get inside!
(INDISTINCT SPEECH)
Lay down on the ground.
(GROANS)
STERLING:
(INDISTINCT SPEECH) man!
(STERLING GROANS)
STERLING:
The fuck, man!
Oh, it's too tight, man!
(STERLING GROANS)
Out of your jurisdiction,
ain't you?
STERLING:
Oh, too tight, man!
(STERLING GROANS)
Sup, Bull?
BULL:
Same old same.
Just another day
on the res, huh?
Day in, day out.
Is this your boy?
We're clear.
You're good, man.
Just come with me.
You good.
You don't need to see this.
Come on. It'll be all right.
DARIUS:
Hey, hey. Not you, Momma.
Sit down.
Crew's had a busy night.
You out shankin' civilians now?
I'm just hanging
with the family.
Don't fuckin' lie to me.
Where's your boy Richie?
No idea, Officer Dumphrey.
Fuck you lookin' for over there?
Ain't shit over there, man.
Ow! What the fuck!
Shut your mouth!
You want C.P.S. up here
on a child welfare notice?
Sit down.
God damn, when will you people
fucking learn, huh?
(GROANS)
DARIUS:
Fuck are you? What is your name?
I don't believe
we've had the pleasure.
I'm not from around here.
He asked for your name,
dip shit.
STERLING:
Simon. Simon Ambrose.
-How old?
-STERLING: 30.
Where are you from,
Simon Ambrose?
Wyoming. Wind River.
Are you lying to me
about your name, Simon?
No, officer.
'Cause when I'm standing
in a res flophouse
and I'm looking for some
wanted drag Indians,
and I meet some random ass,
half-breed white boy
who says he's from Wind River,
then I have my doubts.
All right, what's his name?
Here, stand up. Stand up.
What's his name?
Deputy, how's this house
look to you?
It's fucking disgusting.
It's not fit for a child.
That's what the report will say.
Sterling Gambler.
Hey, the truth comes out!
You're under arrest
for assault and obstruction.
I didn't assault anybody, man.
I don't know how they do it
in the big city.
But when I see a girl
this badly beat,
the drunk gang bangers with her
are usually gettin' booked.
STERLING:
Ain't nobody beat motherfucker.
Get the fuck off me.
BULL:
Leave me.
Hey, you motherfucker!
ANGEL:
Fuck no, you didn't just hit me?
Is that all you got
(INDISTINCT SPEECH)
Fuckin' bring it!
BULL:
I'll kill you, motherfucker!
(♪♪♪)
DUNCAN:
You look tired, Teddy.
Been working some long days.
Not getting enough sleep.
That's not what I meant.
You look spent.
Wore out, like my boots.
Trying to keep this place
from eating itself.
Hadn't been this bad
since back when...
Probably been that long
since I slept through a night.
From nowhere we came,
from nowhere we go.
That is the breath
of the buffalo
in the wintertime.
What?
You come see me
and didn't expect some wisdom?
We've been down before.
Truth is,
you single-handedly set
the whole tribe back.
It wasn't
that scumbag pedophile
or what he did to the kids
or anything.
It was your dumbass fault.
You believe that shit?
That the shit you tell yourself?
DUNCAN:
Jesus, Teddy. Get some sleep.
Take a vacation.
Dyani will thank me.
DUNCAN:
Your life is worth more
than those days.
(♪♪♪)
Okay, so how do we get
out of this?
I gotta work soon.
They'll move.
(SINGS IN NATIVE LANGUAGE)
I swear to God
I've not seen so much
bison shit in all my life.
I mean, my God.
DUNCAN:
It's a lot.
(♪♪♪)
All right, I'm off. Where's Mom?
She's out front, I think.
(♪♪♪)
Hey, come here.
What?
Come here. Give your pops a hug.
Dad, you're hilarious.
(LAUGHS)
(♪♪♪)
You would have done
the exact same shit.
-I never would have done that.
-Yes, you would have.
-In a million years.
-Absolutely.
AINSLEY:
All right.
Great work last night, guys.
You ended up grabbing Sterling
before his city warrant
even came across my desk.
He's already on his way back.
Now, that leaves us
with Richie Blacklance.
Now last night,
Richie was involved
in the stabbing incident
on the res,
so he's not here to lie low,
and his crew
ain't gonna roll on him.
And that is exactly why
we can't trust Tribal
to deal with this
shit bird appropriately.
We should have a car
outside Richie's mom's house.
-All right, listen.
-She's gotta know something.
AINSLEY:
I'm already dealing
with enough blowback
from Tribal and the feds
about last night.
We caught
a triple murderer.
AINSLEY:
So we'll handle this,
but it's walking a fine line.
-PHIL: Cop killer.
-Bureaucratic bullshit.
-PHIL: Guy had a family.
-DARIUS: We know he's here.
-DARIUS: We need to hunt him
down.
-All right, everybody.
We have the resources,
that if we find Richie,
we can do this
as safely as possible.
Getting cuffs on him isn't
worth any of you getting hurt.
So stay in pairs,
know where you're at,
know where your backup is.
All right, that's it.
Dismissed.
Hey, stay safe out there.
I already know
what you're gonna say.
-Yeah?
-Yeah.
Not even a heads up, huh?
That's cool.
Honestly, if this whole thing
gets wrapped up
and no one else gets killed,
I could give a shit.
Teddy, are we sure
about Chelsea?
She wants nothing to do
with Richie.
She still blames him
for Leanne's overdose.
Well, what do you think?
Richie was using back then.
Rumor was Luke had his dealer
sell him a hot shot,
trying to take him out.
Richie's sister, Leanne,
she got ahold of it.
Richie blames Luke,
Luke denies it.
But the dealer
who supplied him that hot shot
that killed Leanne,
he's the 1-8-7
out in the city.
What's that tell ya?
That he's here to wreak havoc.
You know, having Richie
in county
is like igniting a powder keg.
Look, I don't need
an officer-involved shooting.
I'm sure you don't want one
on your side either.
TEDDY:
Who's that?
Uh, some girl.
She was getting passed around
and beaten up last night
by, uh, Bull
and Sterling Gambler.
Jake's sister, Angel?
She's Bull's lady,
she didn't get passed around.
Uh, she wouldn't give us
a statement,
and she's got
outstanding warrants with us.
So, she's gonna be
sitting pretty
until her
bail hearing tomorrow.
TEDDY:
Jesus, look what they did
to you.
Your boy okay?
I don't know. Is he?
They took him.
I may lose him.
You won't lose him.
I'll look into it.
You have my word.
But I need your help.
I need to know where Richie
and Albert are laying low.
I'm trying to help that kid.
There's still time for him.
(SOBS)
TEDDY:
But it's better
if I find Albert
before these deputies.
(SOBS)
(TAKES DEEP BREATHS)
(EXHALES)
Damn, okay.
(♪♪♪)
ALBERT:
Do you remember
all the cadence calls
we used to have to do in here?
Yeah, I remember.
We should bring my friend Leon
and paintball
this whole place up.
Can't be bringing
anyone around.
Not while I'm here.
Why?
I got people looking for me.
There's probably some people
looking for you too now.
Albert, come here.
(♪♪♪)
Oh, I wish I would've
known about Brad.
I would've--
I would've done this
all different.
I would've come home
to look after him.
I'm glad I still have time
to look after you.
Make you strong.
'Cause if you're not strong,
your mind will fuck with you.
Brain can betray you, you know?
That's why Brad
did what he did.
(♪♪♪)
You know what this is?
You been here before?
Yeah.
Shit like this happens
when you're weak.
When you're weak,
motherfuckers say
they're gonna help you.
When really,
they just wanna use you.
You can't trust anyone, nephew.
That cop, Teddy. The Chief.
White men in blue disguises.
They want you to feel shame
for your bloodline,
for your warrior spirit.
They call it gangs?
They call it criminal?
Man, that's
the white man's laws, not ours!
You hear me?
This ain't gang shit!
This is fucking family.
This ain't crazy.
It's the most sanity
this world has fucking shown us
in a long time.
They call us monsters?
Fine.
Monsters survive.
(SPITS)
(♪♪♪)
See that?
There's some things you need
to know about Richie.
He's been a shooter long before
this thing in the city.
He is cold fucking blooded.
If he is in there,
and if he does anything
other than to cooperate,
you don't hesitate.
Copy.
Sandra.
Do not give him the benefit
of the doubt.
He will kill you.
Put him down,
and you don't even give him
a chance to think about it.
You hear me?
And Albert?
We're here to save that boy,
but only after we get him
out of here
and only after we get rid
of Richie.
(♪♪♪)
Check these.
(GRUNTS)
(♪♪♪)
RICHIE:
You hungry at all?
ALBERT:
Yeah. Starving, actually.
RICHIE:
Same.
Man, I could go
for a double cheeseburger, man.
RICHIE:
Whoa, what the fuck?
Fuck is that?
DARIUS:
Shit, he's here.
I fucking knew it.
PHIL:
You're right.
Teddy's car's over there.
-Let's get going.
-PHIL: Yeah, let's do it.
-What do you see?
-It's, uh...
Shit, it's cops.
How many?
Two.
They're coming up right now.
Stay in here.
We're leaving soon.
I'll come get you, all right?
(GROANS)
You do exactly as I say.
Exactly.
Son, I am trying
to save your fucking life.
You wanna see your
grandma again,
or do you want her crying
over your corpse too?
(SOBS)
Okay. Okay.
(♪♪♪)
Phil? Phil, sound off!
ALBERT:
Richie!
Darius, look out!
TEDDY:
Take him back,
get him out of here.
SANDRA:
Go, go, go!
RICHIE:
Hey, Teddy, is that you?
Yeah, Richie, it's me.
RICHIE:
I'm glad.
(CHUCKLES)
Damn, I'm on a roll.
You guys kind of suck
at your job.
I'm ready to go. Are you?
RICHIE:
Yeah, that's what
I'm talking about.
I heard you used to get down.
Now you just get down
with chomos, though, huh?
Why don't you go sit
on that couch
and kill yourself, too?
I think you owe that to us.
(MIMICS GUNSHOTS)
(RICHIE CHUCKLES)
You gonna blame me
for you being a psychopath,
Richie, huh?
Bad man touched you funny,
so now you gotta be
-a big, bad gangster?
-RICHIE: Fuck you!
Murderer to undo
all that man loving?
(GROANS)
(CHOKES)
(♪♪♪)
It's-- it's okay.
Say hi to Coach for me.
(♪♪♪)
(INDISTINCT SPEECH)
At least one officer down.
I need help here immediately.
DISPATCHER (ON RADIO):
Two officers down.
I need ambulances.
(RICHIE SNIFFING, GRUNTING)
(RICHIE CHUCKLES)
RICHIE:
Yoo-hoo.
(RICHIE GRUNTS)
RICHIE:
Shit. God damn!
(RICHIE LAUGHS)
RICHIE:
Woo-hoo!
If you come in here,
I'm fucking killing you!
RICHIE:
Oh, you scary.
The cavalry's coming!
You might as well
get the fuck outta here!
RICHIE:
Cavalry?
Hey, that's cold, yo.
The police response out here
is jack shit,
even when it's the pig calling.
What should I do
with Teddy, though?
Take him with me
or just twist this wannabe
native's cap back?
Teddy! Teddy, are you okay?
RICHIE:
He can't really talk right now.
Oh, you should come out
and see him.
He was pleading with me.
"Please. Please, I have a son."
(RICHIE MIMICS CRYING)
You-- you should just--
just use the window.
I won't say shit.
Just-- just go.
(♪♪♪)
(SANDRA GRUNTS)
(RICHIE LAUGHS)
You're just-- you're scrappy,
aren't you?
Yeah, go sleep.
I fucking got you.
I did.
(CHOKES)
(SCREAMS)
CHELSEA:
Richie!
(SANDRA GASPING)
Oh, fuck.
(POLICE RADIO CHATTER)
ALBERT:
Richie! Richie!
(ALBERT CRYING)
Richie!
(CRYING)
It's going to be okay.
(♪♪♪)
(TAKES A DEEP BREATH)
D.E.P Gang Member:
Come on. Let's go.
(♪♪♪)
D.E.P Gang Member:
Jake, let's do it.
Teddy was a good man.
He was here for our people.
And what he did here today,
it won't be forgotten.
(SPEAKS NATIVE LANGUAGE)
(♪♪♪)